Finding Aid for Abraham and Henrietta Epstein Papers 1920-1960
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Abraham and Henrietta Epstein Papers 1920-1960, 1930-1942
Epstein, Abraham, 1892-1942.
5 linear feet
Executive secretary of the American Association for Old Age Security (name later changed to American Association for Social Security.) Subject files relating to his work in behalf of the elderly poor and the unemployed worker; also collected papers of his wife Henrietta Epstein on the subject of social security.
88287 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was transferred from the University of Michigan Institute of Gerontology (donor no. 6160 ) in 1985. Additional papers were received in 1987.
The collection is open for research.
Abraham Epstein was born in Liubarn, Russia, in 1892, and immigrated to the United States in 1910. After graduation from the University of Pittsburgh in 1917 and work on his masters degree at Columbia University, he embarked upon a lifelong crusade for enactment of adequate old age, unemployment, and health insurance programs.
After six years with the Pennsylvania Commission on Old Age Pensions, and three with the Fraternal Order of the Eagles (during which he worked with the aged), Epstein became a founding member and executive secretary of the American Association for old Age Security (AAOSS). Epstein and the organization, which changed its name to the American Association for Social Security (AASS) in 1933, conducted a tireless campaign on behalf of the elderly poor and unemployed worker, and were a contributing factor in the passage, in 1935, of the Social Security Act. Thereafter, Epstein, who was critical of the limitations of the act, constantly prodded and worked for improvements in it, and strove for a social insurance program that meant "social safety for Americans."
In addition to his work with the AASS, Epstein was a noted lecturer and author, and taught for many years at Brooklyn College and New York University. He died after a short illness in 1942, at the age of fifty. He was survived by his wife, Henrietta.
The Abraham Epstein papers at the Bentley Historical Library provide the researcher insight into the careers of Abraham Epstein and Henrietta Epstein. Abraham Epstein's writings and portions of his correspondence demonstrate the depth of his commitment to social security and offer a look at his version of the ideal social security program. The papers, however, provide little insight into the workings of the AAOAS and AASS - organizations which were a vital and integral part of Abraham Epstein's life. It is only through study of the man and the organizations behind which he was the driving force that a thorough appreciation of his role in the social security movement can be gained.
The Abraham Epstein papers at the Michigan Historical Collections are divided into two subgroups: Abraham Epstein and Henrietta Epstein. Both subgroups are further divided into two series: Correspondence (arranged topically), and Topical Files.
The papers should be used, therefore, to supplement other manuscript collections on deposit in the state of New York. Columbia University holds the Abraham Epstein Papers (86 boxes), and the AASS papers (123 boxes) are located at the Labor-Management Center at Cornell University. Finding aids for the New York collections are available for use by researchers.
Subjects:
American Association for Old Age Security.; American Association for Social Security.; Epstein, Abraham, 1892-1942.; Old age.; Social security.
Contributors:
Epstein, Henrietta.
- Abraham Epstein
  Of interest to the researcher are Abraham Epstein's files of correspondence with the Social Security Board, in which he discusses his views of the theory, content, and implementation of the Social Security Act. In his Topical Files, there are extensive holdings of articles and writings, many issues of the AASS monthly bulletin, and interesting industrial handbooks, published in the 1920s, from various British Isle firms. The pension and insurance programs of European firms shaped, in part, Epstein's early views on social security.
  - Correspondence
    - Addams, Jane undated (Box 1)
      one card, routine
    - Advisory Committee on Social Insurance 1942 (Box 1)
      (letters to and responses of those asked to serve on the committee)
    - British Isles Firms, re: Pension Programs 1925 (Box 1)
      (includes printed materials, see also Topical Files)
    - Fundraising
      - General undated, 1930-1933, 1939 (Box 1)
        (samples of letters and responses)
      - Luncheon 1942 (Box 1)
        (mostly samples of replies to invitations)
      - Gray, Professor Herman 1933-1935 (Box 1)
        (mostly re: New York unemployment insurance law)
    - Harper's article: "Our Social Security Act" Undated, November 1935-January 1936 (Box 1)
      (mostly comments on the article, which was written by Epstein)
    - Matthews, William 1930-1933, 1935, 1938, 1943 (Box 1)
      (Matthews was Director, Department of Family Welfare, Association For Improving the Condition of the Poor, and Director of Special Services, Community Services Society of New York, mostly re: Old Age Insurance)
    - Memoranda re: Social Security 1941 (Box 1)
    - Nordholm, Alex 1935 (Box 1)
      (interesting correspondence re: the Social Security Act)
    - Ohio Old Age Pension League 1929, 1932, 1933 (Box 1)
      (re: League activities, includes printed material)
    - Pennsylvania Federation of Labor 1920-1922, 1927 (Box 1)
      (mostly re: workers education, includes two President's reports and note from Henrietta Epstein re: Epstein's efforts to establish a Workers' Education Bureau)
    - Roosevelt, Franklin D., undated 1928-1931, 1934, 1940 (Box 1)
      (mostly re: passage of a New York Old Age Pension bill)
    - Senators 1942-1943 (Box 1)
      (state and national, re: various legislative bills)
    - Social Insurance Conference Group, primarily 1936 but includes 1940 (Box 1)
      (mostly re: its principles of social insurance)
    - Social Security Board 1935-1943, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Social Security: Miscellaneous
      (re: state and national programs, includes letters to the editors)
      - 1938 undated (Box 1)
      - 1939 (Box 1)
      - 1940, 1942 (Box 1)
    - Stone, I. F. 1933 (Box 1)
      (copy of 1933 letter from J.B. Andrews, of the American Association for Labor Legislation, to Stone that is critical of Epstein's work with unemployment insurance)
    - Tenth Anniversary of American Association for Social Security (AASS) 1937 (Box 1)
      (letter to Gifford Pinchot asking for statement on accomplishments of the Association; also a list of names of others written to)
    - Miscellaneous 1930-June 1943, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Topical Files
    - Biographical (Box 2)
    - Advisory Council on Social Security Final Report December 10, 1938 (Box 2)
    - American Association for Social Security 1927-1943 (Box 2)
    - Articles, Memoranda, Reviews, Letters to the Editor: By Epstein, 8 folders (Box 2)
      (alphabetically by title)
    - Articles, Reviews, Statements, Letters to the Editor: By Others.
      (alphabetically by last name)
      - A-Z, 7 folders (Box 2)
      - Witte, Edwin, 5 folders (Box 2)
    - Association Publications
      - Article (Social Security in Wartime and After) 1942 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous from both the AAOAS 1929-1941 (Box 3)
      - Summaries (Social Security in the United States) 1934-1941 (Box 3)
    - Board of Directors Meeting, A.A.S.S., Minutes October 4, 1933 (Box 3)
    - British Isles Firms: Working Conditions and Rules, 4 folders (Box 3)
      (mostly handbooks from the 1920s and includes pension program information)
    - Camp Tamiment 1943 (Box 3)
    - "Challenge of the Aged, The" (Epstein manuscript) (Box 3)
    - Compulsory Health Insurance ("A Practicing Surgeon Looks at Health Insurance," by Bertram Bernheim) 1940 (Box 3)
    - Compulsory Health Insurance bill summary 1940 (Box 3)
    - Consulting Work (Box 3)
    - Contributors 1929-1938 (Box 3)
      (lists of names and amounts given; includes 1933 financial report to Epstein)
    - Course and Lecture Notes undated (Box 3)
    - Dependent Parents 1940 (Box 3)
      (interesting case studies)
    - Fiftieth Anniversary Dinner, American Association for Social Security 1942 (Box 3)
    - Miscellanea 1933, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Monthly Newsletters (Bulletin of the American Association for Old Age Security)
      - June 1927, December 1927, 1928 (Box 3)
        (missing January, August, November, December)
      - 1929 (Box 3)
        (missing February, December)
      - 1930 (missing February, March), 1931 (name changes to Old Age Security Herald) (Box 3)
      - 1932-1933 (Box 3)
        (missing June-September, 1932)
        (name changed to Social Security in July-August 1933)
      - 1934, 1935 (Box 3)
        (missing January, June-December)
      - 1937, 1940-1944 (Box 3)
        (miscellaneous copies)
    - New York University, Report of the Chancellor contains reference to Epstein's death 1941-1942 (Box 3)
    - Pennsylvania Commission on Old Age Pensions 1919 (Box 3)
      (Report while Epstein was director)
    - Social Security Act Amendments 1939 (Box 3)
    - Speeches undated, 1934, 1935 (Box 3)
    - Testimonial Dinner in Epstein's honor 1942 (Box 3)
    - Testimony before House Committee on Labor, re: Old Age Pensions 1930 (Box 3)
    - Unemployment articles (arranged alphabetically by author) 1925-1941, 4 folders (Box 3)
- Henrietta Epstein
  The Henrietta Epstein files are comprised primarily of documents collected, rather than generated, by her. The major portion of the series is fourteen folders labeled "Collected Documents," which contain printed materials from a variety of organizations that pertain to the field of social security. Such documents include congressional bills, speeches, and hearings summaries; Committee For The Nation's Health newsletters, National Consumer League bulletins; reprints of articles and speeches; Social Security Agency bulletins; and so forth.
  - Correspondence
    - A.A.S.S.: Collected Files of the Executive Secretary (1 letter) 1941 Acting Executive Secretary, 1942 and Associate Secretary, 1943 (Box 4)
      (mostly routine, but includes interesting correspondence from 1943 re: the proposed merger of the A.A.S.S. and the American Association for Labor Legislation)
    - Miscellaneous 1939-1962, 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Topical Files
    - A.A.S.S. (miscellaneous, routine) (Box 4)
    - American Pension Committee (official publication "The Senior Citizen") 1958, 1961 (Box 4)
    - Canada ("Canada Plans Security") 1944 (Box 4)
    - Collected Documents (Box 4)
    - Great Britain
      - Social Services 1943-1945, 1946, 1948, 1949-1951 (Box 4)
      - Beveridge Plan 1943 undated (Box 4)
    - Industrial Union Department (scattered issues) 1943, 1959-1963 (Box 4)
    - International Social Insurance Conference report submitted by Henri Raynaud at 8th General Meeting 1947 (Box 4)
    - International Social Security Association Bulletin 1949 (Box 4)
    - Interstate Conference on Non-Occupational Disability Benefits Program 1949 (Box 4)
    - Letters to the Editor (in the New York Times), 1942 undated, 1944-1945 (Box 4)
    - New York, City of
      - Health and Health Insurance 1944-1946, 1950 (Box 4)
      - Welfare, Department of 1944 (Box 4)
    - New York, State of
      - Disability
        - Labor and Related Bills 1951 (Box 4)
        - Pamphlets 1947, 1948, 1951 (Box 4)
      - Health and Health Insurance pamphlets 1957 (Box 4)
      - Unemployment
        - Advisory Council on Placement and Unemployment Insurance 1948 (Box 4)
        - Unemployment Insurance Advisory Council 1945-1946 (Box 4)
    - Party Platforms (Economic Education Subcommittee) 1948 (Box 4)
    - Poland (Social Legislation) 1948 (Box 4)
    - Social Security
      - Disability
        - Article by R.A. Hohaus, "Compulsory Cash Sickness Benefit Plans-Some Practical Problems" 1946 (Box 4)
        - Federal Security Agency 1944, 1949 (Box 4)
        - Miscellaneous undated, 1950 (Box 4)
        - National Consumers League 1948-1949 (Box 4)
      - General
        - Forum Discussion Scripts for WGED Radio 1943-1945 (Box 4)
          (re: Social Security and Unemployment Insurance)
        - National Conference on Social Security (Address, "Social Security in America") 1944 (Box 4)
        - Pamphlets
          - 1945 (Box 4)
          - 1947 ("Building America") (Box 4)
      - Medicare 1953, 1960 (Box 4)
      - National Health Assembly Meeting May 1-4, 1948 (Box 4)
      - National Health Insurance
        - Articles and Notes undated, 1945-1948 (Box 4)
        - Committee for the Nation's Health
          - Bulletins and Memos 1947-1952 (Box 5)
          - Hearing Highlights undated (Box 5)
          - Press Releases (Box 5)
        - Congressional Bills 1945-1947 (Box 5)
        - Miscellanea (Box 5)
        - Newspaper Article, "Should Medicine Be Socialized" 1948 (Box 5)
        - Newspaper Clippings 1939-1943 (Box 5)
      - Old Age and Survivors Insurance
        - Article, "Living in Retirement: A Moderate Standard for an Elderly City Couple," by Mollie Orshansky 1968 (Box 5)
        - Articles 1943-1944 (Box 5)
        - Bills 1948 (Box 5)
        - Committee Reports 1948-1950 (Box 5)
        - Editorial Excerpts 1948 (Box 5)
        - Federal Security Agency
          - Pamphlets 1943-1950 (Box 5)
          - Summaries and Statements 1944-1954 (Box 5)
          - Summary of Hearing on H.R. 6000 before Senate Finance Committee February-March, 1950 (Box 5)
        - The Townsend Plan (H.R. 4471) 1956 (Box 5)
      - Unemployment
        - Alaska Unemployment Compensation Commission reports 1946-1947, 2 folders (Box 5)
        - Altmeyer, Arthur J., "Persistent Problems in Unemployment Compensation" address given before Interstate Conference of Employment Security Agencies 1944 (Box 5)
        - Massachusetts Special Commission Relative to the Employment Security Law, Supplementary Report 1948 (Box 5)
        - Miscellanea 1943-1949 (Box 5)
      - Wagner-Murray-Dingell
        - Articles 1944-1945 (Box 5)
        - Bill 1945, 1949 (Box 5)
        - Miscellanea 1944-1945 (Box 5)
    - Speeches, Reports, Talks
      - Undated (Box 5)
      - 1943-1946 (Box 5)
    - YWCA
      - 1947-1948 (Box 5)
        (mostly reports re: federal financing of health care, and the Taft Bill, also includes minutes of an Economic-Committee meeting)
      - 1951 (Box 5)
        (materials from New York State Division of Placement and Unemployment Insurance)